In sha Allah ho Ta'ala(إن شاء الله), this will be our last session on the life of our great leader,
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه و رضي الله عن الصّحابة أجمعين .
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, as we know and seen by going through his biography,
was very strict in his rules.
Umar bin Khattab رضي الله عنه wanted Madina to be pure and clean from all of the contaminations,
if we would call it, that were occurring in the periphery of the Islamic world,
where people were just embracing Islam
and where you had Ahl-Uz-Zimmah(أهل الذمه) and non Muslims.
It was a blend and a mixture.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wanted Madina to be far away from that.
Therefore, he did not want to have, any non Muslim slaves in Madina.
Now, obviously, non Muslim freemen, were not allowed in Madina to start with,
based on the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ of,
أَخْرِجُ الْمُشْرِكِيْنَ مِنْ جَزِيْرَةِ الْعَرَبْ
Drive the Mushrikeen(مشركين) out of the Arabian Peninsula, and Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لَا يَجْتَمِعْ فِيْهَا دِيْنَانْ
No two religions should be combined in Arabia.
However, since slaves, do not have free choice and they are part of the property,
they were not seen as a violation of this rule of Hadith(حديث).
However, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wasn't comfortable having them in Madina,
and by the way, we will mention the word slaves and slavery here.
Unfortunately, the word today, doesn't mean, what it meant to the Sahabah(صحابه) yesterday.
Slavery in the European context was based on racism.
It was one color enslaving another.
And that's a completely different concept
than the slavery that existed in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه).
In the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ and Sahabah(صحابه),
they were living by international law that existed, of the time,
and that is that prisoners of war become slaves,
no matter what their color is, what their background is,
Arabs can be slaves,
Africans can be slaves, European can be slaves, Persian can be slaves
and that was something at least around Arabia,
that was how the situation was with the Roman and Persian Empire.
However, the difference was that
other people or other religions were enslaving people and we're very brutal in their slavery.
However in Islam, slavery was just like a job, and it was a very accommodating job.
So the slaves would have to eat from the same food that the master eats.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want the slaves to be separated from the eating places of the free men,
so they would eat all together.
It's not like you have separate quarters for the slaves where they eat,
and then the Freeman eat in a different place.
No! They would eat together.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not allow, disciplining them brutally
and they need to be treated with compassion.
Rasool Allah ﷺ  said: They are your brothers.
In fact, Rasool Allah ﷺ before he passes away,
his last advice to the Ummah(امة) was?
Salah(صلاة) and be kind to your slaves.
أَلصَّلَاةْ ، وَمَا مَلَكَتْ أَيْمَانُكُمْ
This was his last advice to the Ummah(امة).
So, they are treated very well and
because of this good treatment and because they had free opportunity, like everybody else,
slaves many of them became scholars, many of them became army generals.
Possibly Tariq Bin Ziyad(طارق بن زياد) was a slave and he was the one opened Andalus(ألأندلس) .
Attaa(عطاء) was a former slave and he was considered to be the greatest scholar of Makkah(مكه)
in his time, in the era of a At-Tabaeen(ألتابعين).
Nafea(نافع) who was the salve of Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر).
He was the carrier of the knowledge of Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر),
he was a transmitter of that knowledge.
What is referred to as the golden chain of narration in Hadith(حديث)
is Malik(مالك),
An(عن) Nafie(النافع),
Ann(عن) Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر)
Ann(عن) Rasool Ullah
Imam Malik(إمام مالك) was his An-Nafea(النافع) student, by the way,
Imam Malik(إمام مالك) was a student of the slave.
This golden chain of narration is Malik(مالك) narrating from An-Nafea(النافع),
narrating from Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر), narrating from Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and there's some Ahadith(احاديث) where Ash-Shafie(أشافعي),
because Ash-Shafie(أشافعي) was a student of Malik(مالك),
and Ahmad(أحمد) was a student of Ash-Shafie(أشافعي),
you have some Ahadith(احاديث),
Ahmad(أحمد) narrating from Ash-Shafie(أشافعي), narrating from Malik(مالك),
narrating from An-Nafea(النافع), narrating from Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر).
So, you can add more gold to that chain.
So, don't carry the same connotations of slavery today
and apply them to slavery yesterday, it was a completely different thing.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want these slaves, who were taken in war.
He did not want them in Madina.
However, some of Sahabah(صحابه) were lobbying for having them in Madina,
because they were the basis for their business.
And Al-Abbas Bin Abdul-Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبدالمطلب) was one of them.
And he had the most slaves in Madina and it was an income generating thing for him.
So, he was lobbying Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه to allow them into Madina
and Umar(عُمَر), because of the pressure of the Sahabah(صحابه) agreed to have them in Madina.
One of these slaves, he's Persian from Faris(فارس)
he was good in making stone Mills, he was a good skilled worker.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه was approached by this man, his name is Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ).
He told Umar(عُمَر): My master Al-Mugheera Bin Sho'ba(ألمغيره بن شعبه) is charging me too much.
So, this man would work and Al-Mugheera(ألمغيره) would take part of the profits.
So, can you ask him to reduce my payments.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
إِتَّقِى اللهَ وَأَحْسِنْ إِلَى مَوْلآكْ
Fear Allah and be good towards your master.
So, this man turned around and he said to himself.
يَسَعُ النَّاسَ عَدْلُه’ غَيْرِيْ أكُلٌ النَاسِ يَسْعَهُمْ عَدْلُه’ إلَّا أنَا
His justice is sufficient for everyone except me.
He is just with everyone except myself.
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him that,
with the intention of going to Al-Mugheera(ألمغيره) and asking him to reduce the payments.
But that was the way of Umar(عُمَر) he would give advice to both sides.
but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not tell him, Well I'm going to go to Al-Mugheera(ألمغيره),
he just told them, fear Allah and be good to your master.
And then he went to Al-Mugheera(ألمغيره)
and he told Al-Mugheera(ألمغيره) to reduce the payments on Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ).
But Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ) has already made the intentions of killing Umar(عُمَر)
and since he was a good skilled worker, he carved out this dagger, which was double edged.
So, you have the handle and then you have the blade pointing from both sides.
So, it could strike both ways.
And it was very well done and then he soaked it in poison,
until it absorbed all of the poison.
Apparently, he went to Hurmozaan(هرموزان) and he asked him,
what do you think about this dagger? He said;
This dagger, if it touches anyone, it would kill him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) passes next to him and he said;
I heard that you are able to make a mill that works on wind, a windmill.
He said: Yes, I do.
And I'm going to make you a mill that everyone in the world would hear about.
Mean I'm gonna grind you on that mill.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) left him and he went and he said;
"تَوَّا عَدْنِ الْعَبْدََ"
The slave has threatened me, but he did nothing about it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wasn't worried about dying.
He didn't care about his personal safety,
he would care about the orphans and the woman of Iraq,
but he wouldn't care about his own safety.
So, he did nothing about it.
He did not have any bodyguards, before that, or after that.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه would enter into the Masjid(مسجد)
and he would straighten the lines saying Istawoo(إستؤو)
and he would straighten them with his hand.
Amr Bin Maimoom(عمروبن ميمون) and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) he said;
Nobody was between me and Umar in Salaat-Ul-Fajr(صلاةالفجر) but Abdullah Bin Abbas(عبدالله بن عباس)
meaning he was in the second row right behind Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
between him and Umar(عُمَر) is Abdullah Bin Abbas(عبدالله بن عباس).
And he said: Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه would recite the long Surah(سورة) in the first Rakay(ركاة)
until the people gathered.
So, he would recite Surat-Al-Nakhl(سورةالنخل) or Surah-Yusuf(سورةيوسف)
or some similar Surah(سورة).
He said: As soon as Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه said: Allah Ho Akbar(الله أكبر),
Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ) attacked him from behind and stabbed him on his shoulders
and then he stabbed him again in his waist and that was the one that killed him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), He said;
"أكَلَنِ الْكَلْبْ، أوْقَتَلَنِ الْكَلْبَ"
The dog has eaten me, or the dog has killed me.
That was the first statement that he made,
"أوْقَتَلَنِ الْكَلْبَ .."
The dog has killed me and he doesn't know who it is.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was struck, was stabbed twice
and then Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ) went on a killing rampage.
Whoever, he would see in front of him, he would stab him.
So, he stabbed 13 people, seven of them died.
And then, one of the Sahabah(صحابه), obviously, they were not armed and the Masjid(مسجد),
they weren't carrying their weapons, there were no security guards,
the Khalifah رضي الله عنه would come in without any guards.
So, one of the Sahabah(صحابه) what he did.
He threw a Thaub(ثوب) a cloth, over him.
When Abu Lulu'u(أبولولؤ) knew that he would be arrested.
He slaughtered himself and he committed suicide.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, He held the hand of Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) who was behind him,
and he pulled him to the Mihraab(محراب) to lead the Salah(صلاة)
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه , is the one who led the Salah(صلاة) and he made the very short Salah(صلاة).
Now, Amr Bin Maimoon(عمروبن معمون) said;
We were there and we saw what happened,
while the rest of the Masjid(مسجد) didn't know, what was going on.
So, when Umar(عُمَر) went quiet, they started saying,
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله).
They didn't know what was happening.
And then Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) stepped in and he finished the Salah(صلاة).
And he made a very short Salah(صلاة),
the Salah(صلاة) was very short,
unusual for Salat-Ul-Fajr(صلاةالفجر) which was very long in time of the Sahabah(صحابه),
they would come out and it's already light.
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was carried away.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) the first thing he did, he asked Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس)
to go and see, who is the one who stabbed him.?
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) went and he came back and he said;
It was the slave of al-Mugheera Bin Sho'ba(ألمغيره بن شعبه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
"قَاتَلَهُ الله"
May Allah kill him,
I was good towards him. I did him a favor,
he interceded on his behalf to have the payments reduced on him
and then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
ألحمد لله ألَّذي لَمْ يَجْعَل مِيْتَ تِيْ عَلى رَجُلٍ يَدَّعِ الّإسْلَام
Praise be to Allah, who did not make me die, on the hands of somebody who claims to be a Muslim,
Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدالله) that the one who killed me, is the disbelievers, a Kafir(كافر)
because, I don't want somebody to come on the Day of Judgment arguing with me using
لا إله إلله
and then he said;
لَقَدْ كُنْتَ أنْتَ وَأبُوكْ تُحِبَّانْ أنْ يَكْثُرْ أَلْعَبِيْدْ فِيْ الّمَدِيْنَه
You and your father ....
"أَنْ يَكْثُرُ ألْعَلُوْجْ فِي الّمَدِيْنَه"
You and your father, wanted there to be a lot of disbelievers in Madina.
He's referring to these slaves.
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) said: If you want, we will kill them.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: No! You're not going to kill them,
after they learned your language and they prayed your Salah(صلاة)
and they make Hajj(حَجْ) with you.
Now, you want to kill them after many of them already embraced Islam.
So, this is, what happened in the Masjid(مسجد), with Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
that is how he was stabbed.
Now, they gave Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) milk to drink
and the milk came out from his injury.
"فَعَلِمُوْ أنَه’ مَيِّتْ"
They knew that he's gonna die.
That's it, there's so much internal damage, that his stomach cannot hold food
and they knew that he's going to die.
So, they're all now, planning for that
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) has already given his instructions regarding the Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
That it's the Council of six, as we mentioned last night in the dream that he saw,
he appointed the Council of six
Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه,
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
Sa'ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعدبن أبي وقاص),
Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف),
Talha Bin Obaidellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله)
and Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام).
And all of the six are among the 10, who were given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
The only one of the 10, who was in Madina and was excluded from the group
was Saeed Bin Zaid(سعيد بن زيد),
why?
Because he was from the clan of  Bannu Udae(بنوعدي),
the clan of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Because he was from his clan, he excluded him.
People were asking him to include Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر).
Once somebody, came to him and said;
You should give the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) to Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر),
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) responded and said,
you're not, you're not doing that for the sake of Allah,
you are not saying that for the sake of Allah.
So, these six are the council.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) gave them his clear instructions,
he said: They gather in a house, for a maximum period of three days
and they deliberate, the issue among them and choose one from among them.
They cannot choose somebody, from outside.
It has to be one of these six. He said;
ألَذِيْنَ تُوُفِّيَّ أنْهُمْ الرَسُوْل وَهُوَ عَنْهُمْ رَاضِيْ
These are the six whom, the Messenger of Allah is pleased with when he died,
so it has to be one of the six.
He said: Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر), can attend with them,
but he has no right, to be part of the council.
And he said: He only attends,
in case, you split three and three then you take his opinion, to outweigh the scale.
So, Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) his role is, if they have split and even split,
then his voice would count as seventh.
And he also said: Follow the advice of Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف)
because he said about him.
رَشِيْدٌ مُسَدَّدْ لَهُمْ مِنَ اللهِ حَافِظْ فَسْمَعُ مِنْه’
He said: Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) is a wise man,
who has a clear vision and he is supported by a Hafiz(حافظ) from Allah,
he is protected by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So, listen to him, listen to him.
Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) was one of the closest advisors of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and Umar(عُمَر) used to consider him to have a special mind and ability
because of some insight, which Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is giving him, it is a Hafiz(حافظ) from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Abdur-Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) is the man whom, they say he can turn rocks into gold.
He was by far the wealthiest among the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) appointed Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), Abu Talha Al-Ansaari(أبو طلحه ألأنصاري),
to had a group of 50 men, strong men from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), he said;
When this group appoint the Khalifah(خليفه) among them, if anyone descends, cut off their heads.
He told Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), he said;
Ansaar(ألأنصار) are the ones, who gave victory to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they are the ones, who will give victory to the Khalifah(خليفه)
and if anyone descends, I give you, my orders and commands to behead them.
The Sahabah(صحابه) would come in, for example Hafsa(حفصه) the daughter of Umar(عُمَر) was crying
and she was praising her father,
Umm-Ul-Mo'mimeen(أم مؤمنين), Hafsa(حفصه), she was praising her father,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told her,
I ask you in the name of the duties that you have towards me,
not to speak about me like that but I cannot control your eyes.
I do not want you to say that about me,
she was going on praising him.
He said: I don't want you to say that about me.
However, your eyes, I can't control them,
if you want to cry, I cannot prevent you, from doing that.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want people to be flattered
he didnot wanted people to praise him.
Now, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was very worried
and apparently, it was visible that he was worried, he was very concerned.
So Abdullah Bin Abbas(عبدالله بن عباس) and some of the Sahabah(صحابه) were coming to Sooth Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and to comfort him.
So, Abdullah Bin Abbas رضي الله عنه came and he told Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
أبْشِرْ بِالْجَنَّةْ يا أمير المومنين، أسْلَمْتَ هَيْنَ كَفَرِ النَّاسْ
وَجَاهَدْتَ مَعَ رسول الله صلى الله على وسلم هِيْنَ خَزَلَه النَّاسْ
وَقُبِضَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وَهُوَ عَنْكَ رَاضِى ،
وَلَمْ يَخْتَلِفْ فِيْ خِّلَافَتِكَ أثْنَانْ، وَقُتِلْتَ شَهِيْدًا
He said: Rejoice with paradise, you became a Muslim when people were Kuffar(كفار)
and you made Jihad(جهاد) with Rasool Allah ﷺ
when people were betraying him, and forsaking him
and Rasool Allah ﷺ died and he was pleased with you
and you are now killed as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه told him;
You mentioned that I'm a companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ and that he is pleased with me
that is a blessing from Allah, and I cannot be credited for it, it is something that Allah gave me
and the concern that you see in my face,
is because of my concern about you and your people.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is saying, the reason why you see me concerned
I'm thinking about you and your people,
I'm thinking about the fate of the Muslims after me
I'm thinking about this Khilafah(خِلَافَه) that's why, I'm concerned
it's not fear of death, it is because I'm concerned with the situation of my Ummah(امة)
and then he said;
واللهِ لَوْ أنًّ لِيْ طِلَاعُ الّأَرْضِ ذَهَبَ لَفْتَدَيْتُ بِه مِنْ عَذَابِ الله عَزُّوْأجَل قَبْلَ ألنّهَارًا
In the name of Allah if I had the whole world full of gold
I would pay it to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْto ransom me from His punishment, before I see it.
when you read statements like this it puts you in shame.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) who's one of the 10 giving the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة)
who has been given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة) on many occasions by Rasool Allah ﷺ
Umar(عُمَر) who was The Statesman, who brought Islam to the world,
Umar(عُمَر) one of the greatest Khulafah(خلفاء) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
Umar(عُمَر) who spread the Islam to the hearts of, thousands and thousands
actually millions of people around the world.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he heard this Sahabah(صحابه), saying
that you should rejoice with Jannah(جنة), you are the companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ
you were given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I wish I can get out of it even
with nothing for me and nothing against me.
وَدَدْتُ لًوْ أَنِّيْ أخْرُجْ مِنْهَا كَفَّافْ لَا لِيْ وَلَا عَلِيْهََ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is desiring that all of his deeds are taken away
and he makes it neutral, he breaks
Yani(يعني) Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) after all of these good deeds and he was still worried
he's still feared Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Therefore, those of us who do something good
then they say: Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), I am a very good Muslim
I'm practicing Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله), I've been praying for these many years
I fasted, I did Hajj(حَجْ), I'm paying zakat, you know, I'm doing everything
and they're so confident about it and they think that,
they have the keys of Jannah(جنة) in their pockets.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه after a long life of Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and worshipping Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, on his death bed was worried that, he's not gonna make it.
You know for us, for us now today, if you make zikr(زكر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
you are so happy for the rest of the day, I've done zikr(زكر)
I mean that's an achievement that's an act of worship
for the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, zikr(زكر) was actually their rest.
When they're making zikr(زكر), they're actually resting, from other works that they would do like
fighting the enemy of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
so for them, zikr(زكر) was rest for the body and it was soothing for their hearts.
Their entertainment was Qiyaam Ul-Lail(قيام اليل).
Now, people would entertain themselves by going to nightclubs.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, would entertain, their hearts by standing and praying to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
They would wait for those moments when they would be alone with Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه passed away as Shaheed(شهيد)
to fulfill the promise of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah صلواةالله وسلام عليه, along with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر) and Uthman(عثمان).
Were standing on the mountain of Uhud(أحَد) and the mountain shook
an earthquake.
Rasool Allah ﷺ placed his hand on the mountain and said;
أثْبُتْ أحُدْ فَإنمَاعَلَيْكَ نَبِيٌّ وَالصِدِيّقٌ وَ الشَهِيْدَيْنََ,
Mountain of Uhud(أحَد) stay firm because on top of you, is a Prophet
a Siddique(ألصديق) and two Shuhadah(شهداء),
Umar(عُمَر) and Uthman(عثمان)
He died as a Shaheed(شهيد), as one of the greatest Shuhadah(شهداء) of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammad صلواةالله وسلام عليه
because Shahadah(شهادة) is an honor and it's a choosing, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ chooses Shuhadah(شهداء)
وَيَتَّخِذَ مِنْكُمْ شُهَدَآء
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ loved Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) so much.
He sent Shahadah(شهادة) to his door steps in Madina.
We talked about the Dua(دُعَا) of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he used to say
اللهم إني أسئلك قَتْلًا في سبيلك وَ مَوةً فِيْ بَلَدِ نَبِيَّكََ
O, Allah I asked you to be killed as a Shaheed(شهيد) and to die in the town of your Prophet
because there is a virtue in dying in Madina and there's a virtue in Shahadah(شهادة)
he wanted them both, and then he would ask himself, the question?
وَأَنَّ لِيَّ شَهَادَةْ وَأَيْنَ فِى الْمَدِيْنَهْ
And how can I get Shahadah(شهادة) when I'm in Madina
because Madina was the heartland of Islam, no danger gets through to Madina
nobody was ever assassinated Madina, he was the first one.
Ibn Qayyim(إبن قيم), when he talks about the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
He said: The Battle of Uhud(أحَد) is a victory, it's not a loss
Ibn Qayyim(إبن قيم) considered it to be a victory in his book on Seerah(سيرة)
he has some Allah Ho-Alam(الله أعلم) how many pages, he just went on, and on, and on, and on
talking about how Uhud(أحَد) is a victory.
He said: Why?
Because it's a gold mine of Daroos(دروس), of lessons.
Yes, it was a loss but because Allah use that loss to teach us all of these lessons, it's a victory.
Because the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah Al-Imran(سورة إلعمران) are commentating on what happened in Uhud(أحَد)
he mentions one of these lessons, the Ayah(آية) that was revealed
ويتخذ منكم شهداء
Allah is going to choose from among you Shuhadaa(شهداء)
it's just choice of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, it's not something, that you can get.
It's something that Allah honors you by giving it to you.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, honored Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and gave it to him.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was standing next to Umar(عُمَر), when he was dead,
and when we say dead, we don't really mean that he is dead because
وَلَا تَحْسَبَنَّ الَّذِينَ قُتِلُوا فِي  سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ أَمْوَات
He is not dead,  he's alive
بَلْ أَحْيَاءٌ عِنْدَ رَبِّهِمْ يُرْزَقُونَ۝
They are given Rizq(رزق) by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and they are insides of green birds
flying in paradise wherever they want.
They just give the commands to the bird they are the pilots of those birds,
they fly with them, wherever they want.
What kind of better simulation game can you get, and it's not a simulation
it's a real thing you're driving that bird you're the pilot and it's flying,
wherever you want in Jannah(جنة).
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) said: I was standing next to Umar(عُمَر),
when I felt the hand on my shoulders and I looked at it was Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
and Ali(علي) spoke the following words, he said;
ما خلَّفْتُ أحَدًا، أحِبُّ أنْ ألّقَى الله بِمِثْلِيْ أمَلِيْهِ مِنْكََ
There is nobody living today, whom I would rather meet Allah with his deeds rather than mine, than you.
He said: I would rather meet Allah with your Amal(عمل) than mine.
This is Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنهsaying that about Umar(عُمَر)
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبد المطلب) was a neighbor of Umar(عُمَر), he said;
I've never seen somebody like him, in his Ibadah(عبادة), night and day
never waste a moment of his life.
The Death of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), we cannot underestimate the effect it had on the Muslims of the day.
Ibn Abbasرضي الله عنه said;
That whenever, I would pass next to a gathering, they would be crying, everyone was crying.
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul-Muttalibرضي الله عنه told the people because the people stopped eating
they lost their appetite, they couldn't eat they were not drinking.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said;
يَا أيُّهَا النَّاسََ إنَّا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قَدْ مَاتَ  فَأكَلْنَا بَعْدَ ه’ أشْرِبْنَا
وَمَاتَ أبو بكر فَأكَلْنَا بَعْدَ ه’ أشْرِبْنَا
لا بُدَّ لِنَّاسِ مِنْ أكلِنْ، وَ شُرْبٍ مَدَّ يَدَّه’ ثُمَ أكَّلََ
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: O people when Rasool Allah ﷺ died, we ate,
when Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) died we ate and we cannot survive today without eating.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), he was weeping and then he said;
إنَّا عمر كَانَ حَسْنَنْ لِلّإسلامِ يَدْخُلُوْنَ فِيْهِ وَلَا يَخْرُجُوْنَ
فَلَمَّا مَاتَ إنْ سَلَمَ ذَلِكَ حَسْن فَالنَّاسُ يَخْرُوْجُوْنَ مِنَ الّاِسْلَامَ
Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه said:
Umar(عُمَر) was the fortress of a Islam
when people come into it, they do not leave
and when he died that fortress fell down.
So, now people are walking out of Islam.
you know it's amazing how one man could do so much for the religion
I mean, even though we don't take it as a standard but it's something that could be mentioned
from a secular point of view not from a religious point of view.
From a secular point of view.
When Michael Hart studied the lives of the great,
the only two Muslims that he chose were Rasool Allah ﷺ and he was number one obviously
and by the way he had to apologize for that in the introduction to his book.
He said;
Some of my readers might not like
the fact that I have chosen Muhammadﷺ to head the list, of my greatest man that ever lived
but he was the only man who was supremely successful on both the secular and religious fronts.
And then he said;
If I would just take Muhammadﷺ the military leader that in itself would qualify him to make it on the list,
not looking at the Prophet, the teacher, the family man
just Muhammadﷺ the military leader alone would qualify him.
He's looking at it obviously from a secular point of view.
Otherwise, the lowest of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ is greater than the greatest Kaffir(كافر) on his list.
But the thing is and he is looking at it from a secular point of view and he said;
My standard was, how wide the influence was and for how long did it last.
The only other Muslim who made it to his list was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
because of his achievements as the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims
within 10 years, how wide Islam has spread.
Abu Obaidah رضي الله عنه before Umar(عُمَر) would die, He would say
إنْ مَّاتَ عمر  رَقَّلْ إسْلام
If Umar(عُمَر) would die, Islam would become weaker.
So, the people would ask him why do you say that?
Islam is not in need of Umar(عُمَر)
why would it become weaker, he would say;
قَالَ سَتَرَوْنَ مَا أقُوْلُوْ إنْ بًقِيْتُمْْ
You will see that what I'm saying is true, if you live after he dies
وَ أمَّا هُوَ فَإن وُلِيَ وَالٍى بَعْدَه’ فأخَذَ هُمْ بِمَا كَانَ عمر يَاخُذْهُمْ
لَمْ يُطِعْ لَه’ النَّاسََ وَلَمْ  يَحْمِلُه’ وَ إنْ ضَعُفَ عَنْهُم قَتَلُُ
He said: Because if the Khalifah(خليفه) after Umar(عُمَر) tries to apply the same strictness and rules of Umar(عُمَر),
people will not accept it, from him.
And if that Khalifah(خليفه) is weak then they would kill him.
Only Umar(عُمَر) could command the people in that firmness
because his personality was suitable for it, if somebody else tries to do it, the people wouldn't buy it
and then Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) said;
ما اُحِبُّ أنَّ لِيْ مَا تَطلُوْعُ عليهِ الشَّمْسََ وَتَغْرُبْ وَاَنْ أبْقَا بَعْدَ عمر، يَوْمً وَاحِدًَ
Even if I would get everything the sun rises on
meaning the whole earth
if you would give me the whole earth and ask me to live for a day after Umar(عُمَر), I would refuse
He wouldn't want to live after Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
How old was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he passed away?
Muawiya Bin Abi Sufiyan(معاويه بن أبي سفيان) says;
تُوُفِيَّ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، وَهُوَ إبْنُ الثَّلَاثٍ وَسِتِّيْنَ
تُوُفِيَّ أبوبكر، وَهُوَ إبْنُ الثَّلَاثٍ وَسِتِّيْنَ،
تُوُفِيَّ عمر، وَهُوَ إبْنُ الثَّلَاثٍ وَسِتِّيْنَ، رواه مسلم
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and he was 63 years old,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) passed away and he was 63 years old,
and Umar(عُمَر) passed away and he was 63 years old.
They were together in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and they died at the same age
and they will be brought together on the Day of Judgment.
They were the closest friends.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said I would remember Rasool Allah ﷺ saying;
I left with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر)
I came with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر),
I went with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر).
Always Rasool Allah ﷺ would mention his name along with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
He was buried by Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه Sohaib(صهيب) and Saeed Bin Zayd(سعيد بن زيد),
these are the three who lowered him in his grave.
Before Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) passed away
he told his son Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر), he said;
Go to Umm Momineen(أم المؤمنين), Ayesha(عائشه)
and tell her that Umar(عُمَر), and do not say Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين)
because I'm no, Ameer(أمير) of the Momineen(مؤمنين) anymore,
say Umar(عُمَر) is asking for your permission to allow him to be buried with his two companions
that room belongs Ayesha(عائشه).
So, it was her property, so he needs to get her permission to be buried in there
and he didn't want it to come as an order from order from Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين),
he said: Tell her that its Umar(عُمَر)
because Umar(عُمَر) is not the Ameer(أمير) of the Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) anymore.
Tell her that Umar(عُمَر) wants to be buried with his friends and come back to me,
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر), he said: I went and I found her crying
and I told her, Umar(عُمَر) is giving you his Salam(سلام),
and he is seeking your permission to be buried with his two companions.
Ayesha رضي الله عنهsaid: I wanted that place for myself.
However, today I'm going to give Umar(عُمَر) favor over myself.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) went back, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
When he saw Abdullah(عبدالله) coming, he said: Have me sit upright,
he was so concerned about it.
And then he told Abdullah(عبدالله), What news do you have?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said: The news that you like,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: There was nothing more concerning to me than that.
But then he said: When I die, go to her again.
Because he didn't want her to take a decision that she might regret.
He said: When I die, go to her again
and tell her that Umar(عُمَر) is seeking permission to be buried with his friends.
If she allows me in than Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله),
if she doesn't take me and burry me with the Muslims.
So, they were carrying the body of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and they brought him in, to the room of Ayesha(عائشه),
and they knocked the door and they said;
Umar(عُمَر) is asking for your permission to come in.
She said; He's welcome.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Ayesha رضي الله عنه, after Umar(عُمَر) was buried, she said;
Whenever, I would come into my room, I would have my clothes wrapped all over me.
I was so shy from Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
even though, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he is buried
but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) his personality had so much respect.
Even when he was in the grave.
She said: I had to have my hijab(حجاب) on, when I come into my room.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Ayesha(عائشه), she said;
مَرَّاعَ إبنِ الخَّطاب عَلِمَ أنَّه’ خُلِقَ غِنَّى إلِّاالّإسلام
Whoever, sees Umar(عُمَر), realizes that he was created to give strength to Islam.
Allah created him, Allah made him, to give victory to this religion.
You know, everything is Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ things don't just happen haphazardly.
It was part of the plan of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ that was ordained
that Umar(عُمَر) would be created for that purpose.
The propagator of this religion, the establisher of its institutions,
the Khalifah(خليفه), who would establish the rule of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on land
and then she said;
كَانَ وَالله أحْوَزِيْعً
He was a very disciplined and strict man.
نَسِيْجٌ وَاحْدةَ
He was made from a different fabric.
قَدْ أعَدَّ لِلْأمُوْرِ أقْرَانُهَا
He has prepared for every affair, the appropriate response.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was so competent, strong, confident
that any situation that arises he would be able to handle it,
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) would say about Umar(عُمَر) these are authentic narrations.
لَوْ أنَّ عِلْمَ عمر وُضِعَ فِيْ كَفَّتِ الّمِيْزَانَ
وَوُضِعَ عِلْمُ الّأرضِ فِيْ كَفَّ لَرَجَهَا عِلْم عمر
If the knowledge of Umar(عُمَر) is placed on one side of the scale
and the knowledge of the whole earth is placed on the other side of the scale,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)'s knowledge would be heavier.
His knowledge is heavier than the knowledge of everyone else, he would say;
إِنِّيْ لَأحْسِبُ أَنَّ عمرذَهَبَبِ تِسْعَتِ أَعْشَارِ الْعِلم
I believe that Umar(عُمَر) has left and he has taken away with him 9 tenth of all knowledge,
nine tenths of the knowledge of the earth departed with the departure of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
He would say;
كَانَ إِسْلَامَ عمرفَتْحً، وَهِجْرَتُه’نَصْرًا، وَإِمَارَته’ رَحْمةَ
The Islam of Umar(عُمَر) was an opening,
his Hijrah(هجرة) was victory,
and his reign was mercy.
Abu Talha Al-Ansariرضي الله عنهwould say;
والله مَا مِنْ أهْلِ بَيْتٍ مِنَّ الّمُسْلِمِيْنَ
إلَا وَقَدْ دَخَلَ عَلَيْهِمْ فِيْ مَوْتِ عمر نَقْصٌ فِي دِيْنِهِمْ وَدُنْيَاهُمْ
In the name of Allah, every single Muslim house,
is deficient in its religion and its Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), because of the death of Umar رضي الله عنه.
The death of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) has caused a deficiency,
in the dean and Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) of every Muslim household.
Hudaifa رضي الله عنه Bin Yaman(بن يمان) would say and this is Sahih(صحيح) narration;
إنَّما كان مَثَلُ الَإسلامِ  أيَّامَ عمر
مِثْلِى مُقْبِلٍ لَمْ يَزَلْ فِي إقبَالٍ فَلَمَّا قُتِلَ أدْبَرْ فَلَمْ يَزَلْ فِي إدْبَارْ
When Umar(عُمَر) was alive, Islam was approaching and was drawing near.
And when Umar(عُمَر) died, it turned around and was drawing further away.
Muawiyah Bin Abi Sufiyan(معاويه ابن ابي سفيان) would say about the first two Khulafaa(خلفاء);
أمَّا أبو بكر فَلَمْ يُرِدِدُّنِيَا وَلَم تُرِدْه،
وأمَّا عمر فَلَمْ يُرِدِدُّنِيَا فَأرَدَتْه،
وَأمَّا نَحْنُ فَتَمَرَّغْنَا فِيْهَا ظَهْرَلِّبَتْنَ
Muawiya(معاويه) when he was Khalifah(خليفه) he would say;
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) did not want this world and this world and not want him,
Umar(عُمَر) did not want this world, but this world was chasing after him.
But us, we have sunk ourselves in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) from front to back.
We have got ourselves buried in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Ali Bin Abdullah Bin Abbas(علي بن عبدالله بن عباس) the son of Abdullah Bin Abbas(عبدالله بن عباس),
he visited the Khalifah(خليفه), Abdul Malik Bin Marwan(عبدالملك بن مروان).
It was a very cold day in Ash-Sham(ألشام), in Syria
and he was in a tent covered with some very fancy fabrics
and he had four heaters with him in the tent, four furnaces very comfortable.
So, Ali(علي) came in and he was shivering because it's very cold.
So, Abdul Malik(عبدالملك) said: It seems to be a cold day.
Ali(علي) said: It is the coldest day that people of Ash-Sham(ألشام) have experienced.
And then Abdul Malik Bin Marwan(عبدالملك بن مروان), started talking about Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
and he was criticizing the attachment of people to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and speaking against it.
And then he said: And here is Muawiya(معاويه), for 40 years.
For the first 20 years, he was the Ameer(امير) of Ash-Sham(ألشام).
And for the last 20 years, he was the Khalifah(خليفه),
and what good did Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) do for him.
May Allah have mercy on Umar(عُمَر).
He was the most knowledgeable among us, when it came to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
He is the man, who knew what Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) was about.
He lived a very disciplined life, a life of austerity.
And he died without being scratched by Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Muawiya(معاويه) said that Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) was pursuing him,
Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) was running after him,
but he did not want Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and he saved himself from it.
الحمد لله رب العلمين
Who allowed us to come together and talk about the Seerah(سيرة) of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
It's a blessing of Allah on us, to live with Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه for these 18 evenings.
We asked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to make us of those who would listen to the words
and follow the best of them. Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
لَقَدْ كَانَ فِي قَصَصِهِمْ عِبْرَةٌ
There are lessons in their stories,
Brothers and sisters, the objective of the stories is not entertainment.
The objective is to take heed,
and to benefit,
and to learn,
and then to apply what you learn.
I'm sure that now, you have more love of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
because that is how, it is with the Saleheen(صالحين).
With the Saleheen(صالحين) the more you know about them, the more you love them,
with the Fasiqeen(فاسقين) the more you know about them, the more you despise them.
The more you study about Rasool Allah ﷺ,
the more you study about the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
the more you study about the Sahabah(صحابه)
the more impressed you become.
But we have to take that into action,
now that we know about Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
if we don't do anything about that knowledge and we sit, on it.
We will be held accountable on the Day of Judgment for knowing that and then doing nothing about it.
Sometimes, it's better to be ignorant then to know
because if you know and you don't do anything you're worst,
you're in a worst situation than somebody who's Jahil(جاهل),
because the ignorant can be excused on the Day of Judgment,
but the knowledgeable cannot.
So, we want to take the life of Umar(عُمَر) into implementation.
Now, the reason why we're talking about the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم is
Because their way, was the best way,
there are many righteous Muslims in every generation in every century
there are good Muslims,
but none of them comes close to the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
We could have chose to talk about the great scholar,
we could chose to talk about the great Mujahid(مجاهد),
we could chose to talk about a great Daiyah(داعيه)
but none of them would come close to the personalities of the Sahabah(صحابه) like Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه,
the Sahabah(صحابه) represent the middle way,
they represent the perfect way,
there is something, of everything that you would find in their lives, that could benefit you,
in your family, in your work, in your Da'wah(دعوة).
You would find the reference, for that in the life of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم they represented the middle way.
So, they were not only doing Da'wah(دعوة).
They were not only doing Jihad(جهاد)
they were not only doing Ilm(علم), but they did them all.
And they gave the right proportion to the different Ibadaat(عبادات).
The problem today with us is,
we're like the blind men who went to visit the elephant in the zoo.
You must have heard of that parable.
Three blind men wanted to go to the zoo,
and experience the elephant.
They've never seen an elephant in their life.
They want to experience what an elephant is.
So, they were taken to the zoo.
One of them grabbed the ear of the elephant,
the other one grabbed the foot
and the third one grabbed the tail,
when they went back home People ask them tell us about the elephant.
So, the first one said: The elephant is very thin and broad.
Second one said: No! that's not right.
The elephant is like a pillar
the third one said: No! No! No! Both of you are wrong.
The elephant is like a rope.
Now they were all right but they were all wrong.
They're all right in describing their experience
but they were wrong in thinking that their experience was the only right one.
So sometimes we find brothers going in one direction, they're running in one direction
all what they want to do is learn knowledge and that's it and forget about anything else
and seeking knowledge is the best thing under the sun
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said, this about the students of Ilm(علم) and the angels ask Allah to forgive them.
Somebody else will go into Zuhud(ذهد) and Ibadah(عبادة) Qayyam-Ul-Lail(قيام اليل) Sayyam(صيام)
and will narrate, all of the Hadith(حديث) about how great all of that is.
Somebody, else will go into Da'wah(دعوة) and say it's very important to guide the people to Islam we need to do that
we will not have the right perspective, until we look at the lives of those Sahabah(صحابه)
How did they spend their time?
What did they do?
What was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) busy with during his Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه, would worship during the night and would fast during the day.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه would go in his nightly patrols
taking care of the needy, among the Muslims.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would spend his day financing
and sending armies to fight Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
That is how, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم spend their time
and they are the they are the greatest generation of this Ummah(امة).
So, we need to follow their way, because their way is the best way.
So let's all learn from the life of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and apply it in our ourselves.
We asked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْto accept from us
this deed of coming together and studying about Umar(عُمَر)
we ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to make us of those who listen to the words and follow the best of them.
We asked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to make us of those, who would not only spread the word about Umar(عُمَر)
but would live the life of Umar(عُمَر) in themselves.
we asked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, finally to bring us together with them, in Jannah(جنة).
I'm sure that you have a lot of questions, about the life of Umar(عُمَر)
and you don't want to ask them because you know that I don't know the answer.
Keep those questions In Sha Allah Ho Ta'ala(إن شاءالله تعالى) when you meet Umar(عُمَر) in Jannah(جنة).
Ask him whatever, you want.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The people of Jannah(جنة) are
عَلَى قَلْبِ الرَّجُلٌ وَاحِدْْ
The people of Jannah(جنة) have their hearts are so much in love with each other
as if it is the heart of one man.
So, when you want to meet with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
he will immediately, accept your request.
And he will give you all the time in the world that you want.
Because in Jannah(جنة), there are no deadlines, there's no limit, it's infinity
it's not a million years, it's not a billion years.
It goes on, and on and on and on.
You know the Energizer Bunny, it will run out of energy, before you die in Jannah(جنة)
because you never will die.
It never ends, so you can meet with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
You can ask him about how he became Muslim.
You can ask him about his Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
you can ask him about his Da'wah(دعوة) you can ask him about his Ibadah(عبادة)
He will give you a month, a year appointment as long as you want.
He has all the time and you have all the time.
إِخْوَانًا عَلَىٰ سُرُرٍ مُتَقَابِلِينَ
You will be brothers reclining on thrones.
After knowing all of this about the Sahabah(صحابه)
and after knowing this about Al-Jannah(جنة)
only an insane person would turn down such an offer.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) said: I don't know how somebody could know about Jannah(جنة) and then sleep
and how can there be anybody who knows about An-Naar(النار) and then sleep
but we are living in a state of sleep, unawareness.
And the problem with many of us they only wake up when they die.
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ us to wake us up, way before that and to grant us Tauba(التوبة)
that will forgive all of our sins
and to make us die as Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) as a shaheed(شهيد)
and to bring us, together with them in Jannat-Ul-Fidausi(الجنة الفردوسي).
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ
I have made many mistakes.
Usually speakers would make the assumption if I made mistakes
they are for myself, but I definitely did make mistakes.
So, these mistakes are from myself.
If there was any good it is from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to forgive us all
سُبْحَانَكَ الله هُمَّ وَبِحَمْدِكْ نَشْهَدُ الله إِلَهَ إِلَّا أَنْت نَسْتَغْفِرُكَ وَنَتُوْبُ عَلَيْكَ
Some of the questions, what we have.
Umar(عُمَر) told Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) to do Jihad(جهاد) at the time of Jumu'ah(جمعه).
Does this mean that Jumu'ah(جمعه) is not compulsory on the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) also
what is the best time to make Dua(دُعَا) on the day of Jumu'ah(جمعه).
Jumu'ah(جمعه) is not compulsory on anybody who's traveling.
Anybody who's traveling and the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) are traveling,
a traveler does have the choice of praying Jumu'ah(جمعه) or praying Zuhar(ظهر).
And the time of Dua(دُعَا) on Jumu'ah(جمعه), some scholars say
it is the time, when the Imam(اِمَام) is on the Mimber(ممبر),
and some other scholars say it is the time right before Maghrib(مغرب) of the Day of Jumu'ah(جمعه),
it's either of these two times, that is the time when the Dua(دُعَا) is accepted.
There's a sister in our school who wears the full hijab(حجاب) and
claims that Islam is not equal or fair to women.
She tells the teachers that in Islam women are not allowed to marry four times, whereas men are.
This goes back to a very serious problem,
which is called Ash-Shubuhaat(ألشبهات), doubts in the hearts.
If a person has doubts in their hearts.
It is not the sin but it is, it can lead to disbelieving in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
so it's not an easy matter.
I mean a person could be committing adultery, they could be drinking,
they could be doing a lot of Haram(حرام)
but they believe in Allah and His message, they have no doubts in them.
However, a person could pretend to be a Muslim doing all of the Ibadaat(عبادات),
but they have these doubts in their hearts
and they could be counted among the camp of Al-Munafiqeen(ألمنافقين).
So we need to be very, very careful when it comes to,
where we stand on the issue of Sharia(شريعة)?
Anything that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said, anything that Rasool Allah ﷺ said
we need to take it and accept it as it is.
And that is the whole point of being a Muslim,
because the meaning of Islam we always say that
the meaning of Islam is peace which is not correct.
The meaning of Islam is Submission.
Islam does not mean peace, Islam means submission.
فَلَمَّا أَسْلَمَا وَتَلَّهُ لِلْجَبِينِ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said about Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل).
When Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was about to slaughter his son, he said: "أَسْلَمَا" They submitted.
That is the fulfillment of the meaning of Islam.
And the reason why Hajj(حَجْ) is such a great Ibadah(عبادة)
is because it involves thing that you do, without knowing the reason why you're doing them.
Why are you going around rock building made out of stone.?
Why do you kiss a stone.?
So submission is very important.
A Muslim is not a Muslim without submitting to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
You might not know the reason, you might not know the wisdom
but you accept it, why because Allah said so.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ said so.
So if I tell you about things that Rasool Allah ﷺ did
and you just don't feel comfortable about them.
What do you do?
I tell you a story that Rasool Allah ﷺ did so and so.
You just don't feel comfortable, you don't think that that's right,
but I tell you that this story is authentic, it's true,
you doubt in your heart, you say there's something wrong with my heart
there's something wrong with the way I see things.
What Rasool Allah ﷺ did was right.
And the reason why I don't like it is because I have a problem.
That's how you should view it.
Because there are going to be things in Shariah(شريعة) that you wouldn't understand
and you might feel that, it doesn't sound right to me. Why?
It doesn't sound right because Jahl(جهل), either because of ignorance,
or because of a Fitrah(فطرة) that has been changed
because the right Fitrah(فطرة) will not have a problem with anything in Shariah(شريعة).
So you'd say that there's something wrong with my Fitrah(فطرة).
I need to change it, I need to fix it.
كُتِبَ عَلَيْكُمُ الْقِتَالُ وَهُوَ كُرْهٌ لَكُمْ
For example, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم they have experienced war
and some of them did not like it when it was prescribed on them, some of them felt uncomfortable,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told them;
وَعَسَىٰ أَنْ تُحِبُّوا شَيْئًا وَهُوَ شَرٌّ لَكُمْ ۗ
We might dislike something but there's a lot of good in it, for you.
So good comes from Allah.
Men marrying four women, a man marrying 100 women
if Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said so, than it's the right thing.
If Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said that as soon as you reach the age of 20,
you need to start standing for five hours a day on one foot, until you die.
That would be the right thing, if Allah said so.
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ doesn't order to do anything except if it's good,
and He doesn't prevent us from doing anything, except that it is evil.
We can talk about the Hikmah(حكمة), of how come a man was allowed to marry four women,
while a woman was not.
But Hikmah(حكمة) is irrelevant, we submit and we accept it.
And I can't stress this point more because
that is the first description Allah give to Al-Muttaqeen(ألمتقين).
هُدًى لِلْمُتَّقِينَ ۝ الَّذِينَ يُؤْمِنُونَ بِالْغَيْبِ
Qur'an is guidance for the Al-Muttaqeen(ألمتقين), the pious ones,
who are they?
The ones, who believe in the unseen.
They believe in things that they never saw.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: It wouldn't make a difference for me
if I see Jannah(جنة) in front of my eyes or if I see Hellfire in front of my eyes
because I have Yaqeen(يقين) it can't make a difference if I see it.
I'm not gonna believe in it, more.
That is Ilm-Ul-Yaqeen(علم اليقين)
that is certain faith.
That's what we need to have, that is Islam.
It's alright, it's fine to look for the wisdom and the Hikmah(حكمة).
However, should not hold back on believing, until you understand the meaning,
otherwise it's gonna be just like any other empirical experiment
you prove it scientifically and it becomes logic.
So where is element of faith, where is the element of Eeman(ايمان).
Where is Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ testing you.
Is it permissible to abstain from marriage in order to be able to be like the Sahabah(صحابه),
to free oneself from having to stay behind and care for one spouse.
You know a person is not allowed to take a vow of celibacy
that is Rahbaniyyah(رهبانية) that is not allowed in Islam,
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tested the Sahabah(صحابه) through their wives and children.
They got married and they had children, and that was a test for them,
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told the ones, who failed in the test,
إِنَّ مِنْ أَزْوَاجِكُمْ وَأَوْلَادِكُمْ عَدُوًّا لَكُمْ فَاحْذَرُوهُمْ ۚ
Some of them stayed behind and they did not make Hijrah(هجرة).
So later on when Makkah was opened and Islam dominated.
They will go back to their wives and children and blame them,
and say it's just because of you, we didn't make Hijrah(هجرة) early.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told them,
إِنَّ مِنْ أَزْوَاجِكُمْ وَأَوْلَادِكُمْ عَدُوًّا لَكُمْ فَاحْذَرُوهُمْ
From among your wives and children are enemies for you so beware.
وَإِنْ تَعْفُوا وَتَصْفَحُوا وَتَغْفِرُوا فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ غَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
But if you are forgiving Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is forgiving, Merciful.
Now, it's too late to blame them, forgive them.
Now, you're opening up the blame game and saying it was because of you.
We missed Jihad(جهاد) and we missed Hijrah(هجرة).
No! Forgive them,
وَإِنْ تَعْفُوا وَتَصْفَحُوا وَتَغْفِرُوا
You should have made that decision to make a move early on, so get married,
if you have some conditions to your wife make those conditions before you get married,
and try to find a companion who is like minded and is willing to help you in what you do.
And the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
in fact Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he sent in his Waseea(وصية) before he died.
He said: And don't hold back the soldiers from going back to their families,
otherwise the progeny of the Muslims will end.
So, the objective of marriage is, for Islam to carry on.
And we said that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would say that
sometimes he would force himself to sleep with his wife and he would say the reason is
because Allah may create a soul that will make Tasbeeh(تسبيح) of Allah.
So marriage has objectives and you have some objectives in life, bringing them together.
Are we allowed to wear contact lenses men plus women?
Medical reasons. Yes! If it's for, if it's those colored lenses.
Than that would not be allowed, Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم).
Is it permissible to perform Wadhoo(وضؤ), ablution with cotton socks?
Anything that has thickness and covers the foot and covers the whole foot,
including the ankles, can be used for a Masseh(مسح).
I have prayed on and off until I was about 23 years old.
That's why I started doing all the five prayers, do I have to make up for Missed Salah(صلاة)?
The Scholars say nothing can make up for a missed Salah(صلاة).
Miss Salah(صلاة) that was missed intentionally without an excuse,
nothing can make up for it.
Just like missing a day of Ramadan(رمضان) without an excuse Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لم يَقضِ عنه صيامُ الدَّهرِ
If he fast for an entire year, it would not make up for that day.
So if you missed us a Salah(صلاة), nothing can make up for it, except a Taubah(توبة),
a strong Taubah(توبة), a Taubah(توبة) of regret,
because the most important pillar of Taubah(توبة) is regret.
إنَّما التوبة النِدم
"Taubah(توبة) is regret."
So, nothing makes it up, except the Taubah(توبة),
and because the sin is great, the Taubah(توبة) needs to be strong.
I'm trying to get married but it has become very difficult because I am a divorcee.
Time is also against me as I am 30 years old.
I feel that my parents are not doing enough to help, and they have the criteria of lineage.
What can I personally do within the Islamic boundaries to find a wife,
would also be grateful for any other suggestions.
Initially I thought this was a sister but here it's a brother.
It's more of a problem for sisters, unfortunately.
And apparently it's also a problem for this brother.
Brothers or sisters, Divorce should not be a stigma on anyone, brother or sister.
The Sahabah(صحابه) divorced, it happens and
people should allow them to carry on with their lives, and start the family again.
This is Zulm(ظلم), this is social Zulm(ظلم), that is committed on divorcees.
They are stigmatized, and nobody wants to come close to them,
and the Muslim community is committing oppression and Zulm(ظلم) against them.
In the time of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, they would not let any man or woman go unmarried,
because this is a blessing of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and everyone is entitled to be part of a family.
Muslims are not like non Muslims who can spend their time in pubs and entertainment
from one partner to another until at the end of their life,
they go to an elderly care house.
Muslims, value, family life,
and for a Muslim, the most important thing in their life is their family.
So do not deprive brothers or sisters from being part of a family if they are divorced.
In fact, maybe definitely one solution to that is to encourage polygamy.
It is to encourage it, not to be against it and to fight it, but to encourage it.
It is a solution for the social ills that are going on among the Muslims.
If it wasn't the solution Allah wouldn't have made it Halal(حلال).
Allah wouldn't have made it Halal(حلال) just to satisfy the desires of men,
Allah made it Halal(حلال) because it's part of the Islamic solution for a healthy society.
So for example, a divorce sister, if she cannot find husband
would be able to get married to somebody who's married,
like many of the Sahabiaat(صحابيات) would do.
And regarding the early question of this brother who doesn't want to get married
because you think it will interfere with his intentions.
A story is mentioned about the wife of Ikrimah(عكرمة),
Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahl(عكرمة بن أبي جهل) was one of the men, who gave a pledge to die in Yarmook(يرموك)
he gave a pledge to die, in other words, a martyrdom operation.
That's what, but in the old days, that’s what he did.
"تبعنا على الموت"
So he jumped into the enemy's army and he died, as a Shaheed(شهيد)
his wife was engaged by Khalid Bin Saeed(خالد بن سعيد).
Khalid Bin Saeed(خالد بن سعيد) saw a dream that he's gonna die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
This Sahabiyyah(صحابية) Umm- Hakkem(أم حكيم), She said,
Why don't you wait until the battle is over and then marry me. He said, No!
I will marry you now because I saw a dream that I will die Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So she said, then let's get married, he died the next day.
Isn't it amazing that she and he would want to get married
when they both know that he's gonna die.
Why because they used to see it as a Ibadah(عبادة)
it was Ibadah(عبادة).
This is something that is impossible will happened today.
But it was Ibadah(عبادة).
Are we allowed to give an Arabic and English version of the Quran to a non Muslim, if not, why?
If the translation is more than the original Arabic
then yes but it should only be given to somebody who's interested and will not abuse it.
And it's better to give out the English only.
The reason why it's allowed is because if majority of a book is not Qur'an,
then we don'tclassify it as a Qur'an because
if we say that anything that includes an Ayah(آية) cannot be given to Kuffar(كفار),
then that will include everything, because almost everything has Ayah(آية) of Qur'an in it.
Even newspapers.
So if a book is considered to be a Mus'haf(مصحف), then it should not be given.
But if the majority of the book is like a Tafseer(تفسير) or it has commentary in it.
It is the non Arabic part that can be given up.
I understand that to do Da'wah(دعوة) is Fardh Ain(فرض عين),
however does that require an individual to work collectively in a Jama'at(جماعة)
first of all, Da'wah(دعوة) is not Fardh Ain(فرض عين), Da'wah(دعوة) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية),
Da'wah(دعوة) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية) it is not Fardh Ain(فرض عين).
Not all of the Sahabah(صحابه) did Da'wah(دعوة).
If it was Fardh Ain(فرض عين) than every single one of them would have practiced Da'wah(دعوة).
And there's nothing in the text of Qur'an or Sunnah(سنة) to prove that it is Fardh Ain(فرض عين).
I'm not saying that it's not important to do it's very important,
however, we need to give it the correct Hukum(حكم) in Shariah(شريعة).
Da'wah(دعوة) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية).
Anything should we do it's better if we do it collectively because Islam is a collective religion.
We do Salah(صلاة) in Jama'ah(جماعة), we do Hajj(حَجْ) in Jama'ah(جماعة),
Umrah(عمرة) is done in Jama'ah(جماعة), this is a Jama'ah(جماعة) religion.
So we need to do work collectively, it doesn't.
But Da'wah(دعوة), we could do individual Da'wah(دعوة) too.
Can I take out the first time buyers mortgage to roof my parents and my family.
The Halal(حلال) alternative is too expensive.
I fear that I am burning my bridges to my Lord by this act, Please advice.
Is it too expensive that you would rather to go to hellfire than pay it.
We are willing to follow Shariah(شريعة), if it's cheap.
If the alternative is cheap, but if it is expensive, we don't want it.
We're measuring everything in the dollar or pound sign
that's how we assess, not in terms of Jannah(جنة) and An-Nar(ألنار).
Like when judge in an Arab country, he was given an equivalent of 20,000 pounds, as a bribe.
He said brother that's not enough for me to get to hellfire, you have to pay me more.
So it's depends on, on how much money is sufficient to make you go to hellfire.
mortgage is Haram(حرام) it is Riba(رباء).
And that's the end of the question.
If there's an emergency situation, then you need to go to the Fuqahaa(فقهاء) of this country
who are qualified to give a Fatwa(فتوى) on this issue, to tell you if it's a necessity or not in your particular situation.
In Islam is it allowed to know the gender of a baby while pregnant.?
Definitely, there is no problem in that whatsoever.
What's the problem of knowing the gender of the baby.
There's no problem with that whatsoever.
The book of the 100 greatest men. It's called The Hundred,
list of the most influential figures in history by Michael Hart(HART).
You mentioned the Hadith(حديث) regarding the Sahabah(صحابه), asking
the Prophet about prayer when Dajjal(دجال) comes what is the answer regarding this question,
and Salah(صلاة) on the first day.? Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
"اُقْدُرُوْا لَه’ قَدْرَهْ"
Give it the right proportion, so that could carry different meanings.
There's a request here to reiterate the references by At-Tabri(ألطبري)
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) by Ales Sallabi(علي الصلابي),
these are the two references that I used.
Suggested readings for Uthman(عثمان), same thing I would go
with the books of Ales Sallabi(علي الصلابي), which are in Arabic,
I don’t really know of English sources to recommend.
When Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) deployed his men in battle,
did all Sahabah(صحابه) go to Jihad(جهاد) or some companions left behind
specifically to teach the people knowledge.
Because in those days this Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية),
he had the authority to hold some of them behind.
They were held behind not to teach
but they were held behind to be advisors of another Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) in Madina,
such as Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), Uthman(عثمان) and Ali(علي).
He prevented them from traveling because they were his advisors.
It wasn't really to teach knowledge because Madina was the land of knowledge.
It was the center of knowledge.
But they obviously did teach others.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
سُبْحَانَكَ الله هُمَّ وَبِحَمْدِكْ نَشْهَدُ الله إِلَهَ إِلَّا أَنْت نَسْتَغْفِرُكَ وَنَتُوْبُ عَلَيْكَ
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE.